Guide to the British Cotton Growing Association Records, 1906 - 1968
Department of Special Collections
British Cotton Growing Association Records,
1906 - 1968
M1335
British Cotton Growing Association
1.25 linear ft. (2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box) ca. 300 maps
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The collection contains annual reports, publications, and ca. 300 maps documenting the activities of the British Cotton Growing Association's activities, primarily in Africa, but also in India and Mesopotamia.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions on access.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2002 Aug.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
The collection contains annual reports, publications, and ca. 300 maps documenting the activities of the British Cotton Growing Association's activities, primarily in Africa, but also in India and Mesopotamia.
The plans and drawings primarily document the cotton gins operated by the BCGA in Nigeria, Nyasaland, and Uganda.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
British Cotton Growing Association.; Cotton growing--Africa, Sub-Saharan.; Africa, Sub-Saharan--History--1884-1960.; Africa, Sub-Saharan--Colonization.; Africa, Sub-Saharan--Economic conditions.; Africa, Sub-Saharan--Social conditions.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Annual reports
  - Annual reports, 1906 - 1907 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual reports, 1919; 1921 - 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, 1924 - 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual reports, 1928 - 1930 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual reports, 1931 - 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual reports, 1936, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual reports, 1941 - 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual reports, 1946 - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual reports, 1949 - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual reports, 1953 - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Annual reports, 1957 - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Annual reports, 1961 - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annual reports, 1965 - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series 2. Publications
  - Cotton growing in the British Empire and exotic countries / by Capt. G.S. Burnham. -- Manchester, England: Sherratt and Hughes, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence re: cotton growing in India. -- (BCGA no. 50), 1912 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cotton baling in West Africa and America. -- (BCGA no. 21), 1907 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cotton growing in Anglo-Egyptian Sudan. -- (BCGA no. 49), 1912 May (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Higson, Henry. The work of the British Cotton Growing Association: report / prepared by Henry Higson, 1908 June (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Himbury, William H. Cotton: a Lancashire contribution to the Empire / by William H. Himbury. -- (BCGA no. 149), 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Himbury, William H. The exploration and development of new cotton fields within the British Empire / by William H. Himbury. -- Machester: BCGA, 1921 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Himbury, William H. India and the Sudan as sources for increasing our raw cotton supplies / by William H. Himbury. -- Machester: BCGA, 1923 July (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Himbury, William H. Iraq to the Sudan, 1932 / by William H. Himbury. -- Manchester, England: BCGA, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Himbury, William H. Northern Rhodesia, Southern Rhodesia, and Nyasaland as sources for increasing our raw cotton supplies / by William H. Himbury. -- Manchester, England: BCGA, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Himbury, William H. The part played by our empire in the production of raw cotton / by William H. Himbury. -- Reprinted from The Journal of the Textile Institute, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Himbury, William H. Some promising empire cotton fields: with special reference to a recent trip through India, Uganda, and the Sudan / by William HImbury. -- London: McCorquodale & Co., [ca. 1926] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Himbury, William H. The Sudan, 1935 / by William H. Himbury. -- (BCGA no. 149). -- Manchester: BCGA, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Himbury, William H. The Union of South Africa as a source for increasing our raw cotton supplies / by William H. Himbury. -- (BCGA no. 99). -- Manchester: BCGA, 1927 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hutton, J. Arthur. Cotton growing in British Colonies / by J. Arthur Hutton. -- (BCGA no. 6). -- Manchester: BCGA, 1906 Mar. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum on cotton growing submitted to the Committee on Industry and Trade, 1925 Apr. 29 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Percival, John. Notes on the cultivation and harvesting of cotton in Nigeria / by by John Percival. -- (BCGA no. 11). -- Manchester: Henry Blacklock & Co., 1906 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reed, J. Howard. Cotton growing within the British Empire / by J. Howard Reed, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Report to the Council on the possibilities of cotton-growing in the Anglo-Egyptian Sudan. -- Manchester: BCGA, 1912 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Report to the Council on the possibilities of cotton-growing in the West Indies: I. John W. McConnel, II. William Marsland, III. Report from the Port of Spain Gazette, Jan. 28th, 1912. -- Manchester: BCGA, 1912 Feb. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Speeches at banquet given to Major the Hon. W.G. Ormsby-Gore, M.P. -- (BCGA, no. 96), 1926 Nov. 19 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Speeches at banquet given to the Rt. Hon. the Earl of Derby. -- (BCGA, no. 80), 1923 June 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Speeches at lunches given to His Excellency Sir Harold B. Kittermaster. -- (BCGA, no. 134), 1937 July 12 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Speeches at luncheon given to His Excellency Sir Bernard H. Bourdillon. -- (BCGA, no. 128), 1935 Oct. 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Speeches at luncheon given to Lt.-Col. Sir John R. Chancellor. -- (BCGA, no. 105), 1928 Nov. 6 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Speeches at luncheon given to the Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin. -- (BCGA, no. 102), 1928 May 16 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Speeches at luncheons given to His Excellency Lt.-Col. Sir Stewart Symes, Aug. 2, 1935 and His Excellency Sir Bernard H. Bourdillon, Oct. 11, 1935. -- (BCGA, no. 129), 1935 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Speeches at luncheon given to His Excellency Sir John L. Maffey, Oct. 2, 1928, and Lt.-Col. Sir John R. Chancellor, Nov. 6, 1928. -- (BCGA, no. 103), 1928 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Stanley, Capt. Lord. Report by Captain Lord Stanley on his visit to the Punjab and Sind. -- (BCGA, no. 111), 1930 Feb. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Sudan Plantations Syndicate, Ltd. and the Kassala Cotton Company, Ltd. and their work in the Anglo-Egyptian Sudan, 1950 Apr. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Transport in Africa: East Africa Commission's recommendations. -- (BCGA, no. 90), 1925 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Uganda Protectorate. The Cotton ordinance, 1952 and the Cotton rules, 1960. -- Entebbe: Government Printer, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The British Cotton Growing Association grant in aid from Imperial funds, 1912 Oct. 29 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Summary of the report to the Board of Trade of the Empire Cotton Growing Committee, [ca. 1920] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - West Indies. Report of the Tropical Agricultural College Committee. -- London: His Majesty's Stationery Office, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series 3. Plans and drawings
  - Romily Golf Club, Ltd. (Othertype 4, Folder 1)
  - Marlboro Gin, Ibadan, Lagos [1 of 4] (Folder 1)
  - Marlboro Gin, Ibadan, Lagos [2 of 4] (Folder 2)
  - Marlboro Gin, Ibadan, Lagos [3 of 4] (Folder 3)
  - Marlboro Gin, Ibadan, Lagos [4 of 4] (Folder 4)
  - Nigeria, no.1 (Folder 5)
  - Nigeria, no. 2 (Folder 6)
  - Nigeria, no. 3 (Folder 7)
  - Nigeria, no. 4. Challowa Ginnery (Folder 8)
  - Nigeria, O/P no. 1, Oshogbo (Folder 9)
  - Nigeria, O/P no. 2, Lokoja (Folder 10)
  - Nigeria, O/P no. 3, Zaria (Folder 11)
  - Nigeria, O/P no. 4, Gusau (Folder 12)
  - Nigeria, O/P no. 5, Funtua (Folder 13)
  - Nigeria, O/P no. 6, Malumfashi (Folder 14)
  - Nigeria, O/P no. 7, Mai-Nichi (Folder 15)
  - Nigeria - miscellaneous (Folder 16)
  - Nyasaland - obsolete plans (Folder 17)
  - Uganda - obsolete plans (Folder 18)
  - Mesopotamia & Rhodesia (Folder 19)
  - Misellaneous no. 1 (Folder 20)
  - Misellaneous no. 2 (Folder 21)
  - Misellaneous no. 3 (Folder 22)
  - Misellaneous no. 4 (Folder 23)